<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CGRN_149" xml:lang="en">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title><idno type="filename">CGRN 149</idno>: Excerpt from the <rs type="textType" key="sacrificial calendar">sacrificial calendar</rs> at Kamiros (concerning sacrifices to the Damateres)</title>
				<author>Jan-Mathieu Carbon</author>
				<author>Saskia Peels</author>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<authority>Collection of Greek Ritual Norms, F.R.S.-FNRS Project no. 2.4561.12, University of Liège.</authority>
				<availability>
					<p>Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike International License <ref target="http://creativecommons.org/" type="external">4.0</ref>.</p>
					<p>All citation, reuse or distribution of this work must contain somewhere a link back to the URL <ref target="http://cgrn.ulg.ac.be/">http://cgrn.ulg.ac.be/</ref> and the filename, as well as the year of
						consultation (see “Home” for details of how to cite).</p>
				</availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<msDesc>
					<msIdentifier>
						<repository>n/a</repository>
					</msIdentifier>
					<physDesc>
						<objectDesc>
							<supportDesc>
								<support><p>Small <rs type="objectType">stele</rs> of Lartian marble, with a simple moulding at
										the top. Somewhat broken at the botton. The front and top sides have been well-worked; the
										back was left rough, presumably for resting against a wall.</p>
									<p><dimensions>
											<height unit="cm">30</height>
											<width unit="cm">12.7 (with the moulding, 15 )</width>
											<depth unit="cm">9.3</depth>
										</dimensions></p>
								</support>
							</supportDesc>
							<layoutDesc>
								<layout><p>Letters: <height unit="mm">8-9</height>.</p>
								</layout>
							</layoutDesc>
						</objectDesc>
					</physDesc>
					<history>
						<origin>
							<p><origDate notBefore="-0050" notAfter="0050">ca. 50 BC - 50 AD</origDate></p>
							<p><desc>Justification: lettering (Blinkenberg).</desc></p>
						</origin>
						<provenance><p><placeName type="ancientFindspot" key="Kamiros" n="Aegean_Islands"><ref target="http://pleiades.stoa.org/places/589836" type="external">Kamiros</ref></placeName>.
								Found near Hagios Phokas, north of Siana. Now in the National Museum of Denmark (Copenhagen).</p>
						</provenance>
					</history>
				</msDesc>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<p>Encoded for EpiDoc schema 8.17 on 01-06-201 by JM Carbon.</p>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<langUsage>
				<language ident="eng">English</language>
				<language ident="grc">Ancient Greek</language>
				<language ident="lat">Latin</language>
				<language ident="fre">French</language>
				<language ident="ger">German</language>
				<language ident="gre">Modern Greek</language>
				<language ident="ita">Italian</language>
			</langUsage>
			<textClass/>
		</profileDesc>
		<revisionDesc>
			<change>Revised by XX in 20XX.</change>
		</revisionDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<facsimile>
		<graphic url="x">
			<desc/>
		</graphic>
	</facsimile>
	<text>
		<body>
			<div type="bibliography">
				<head>Bibliography</head>
				<p>Edition here based on Blinkenberg <bibl type="abbr" n="Lindos II">Lindos II</bibl> 671, with ph. There are no
					problems with the readings.</p>
				<p>Other edition: Segre - Pugliese-Carratelli <bibl type="abbr" n="Tit.Cam.">Tit.Cam.</bibl> 156a.</p>
				<p>Cf. also: Sokolowski <bibl type="abbr" n="LSS">LSS</bibl> 95.</p>

				<p>Further bibliography: <bibl type="author_date" n="Segre 1951">Segre 1951</bibl>; 
					<bibl type="author_date" n="Badoud 2015">Badoud 2015</bibl>: 11-35; 
					<bibl type="author_date" n="Iversen 2017">Iversen 2017</bibl>:
					192-197; <bibl type="author_date" n="Carbon forthc.">Carbon forthc.</bibl></p>
			</div>
			<div type="edition">
				<head>Text</head>
				<ab>
					<lb xml:id="line_1" n="1"/><name type="month"><w lemma="Σμινθεύς">Ζμινθίου</w></name>
					<lb xml:id="line_2" n="2"/><w lemma="τετράς">τετράδι</w>
					<lb xml:id="line_3" n="3"/><w lemma="ἵστημι">ἱσταμένου</w>, <lb xml:id="line_4" n="4"/><name type="deity" key="Damateres"><name type="deity" key="Demeter"><name type="deity" key="Kore"><w lemma="Δημήτηρ">Δαμάτερσιν</w></name></name></name>
					<lb xml:id="line_5" n="5"/><name type="animal" key="sheep"><w lemma="ὄϊς">ὄϊν</w></name>
					<lb xml:id="line_6" n="6"/><name type="quality"><name type="gender"><w lemma="κύω">κυεῦσαν</w></name></name>.
				</ab>
			</div>
			<div type="translation" xml:lang="eng">
				<head>Translation</head>
				<p>On the 4th of Sminthios, to the Damateres (Demeters), (sacrifice) a pregnant ewe. </p>
			</div>
			<div type="translation" xml:lang="fre">
				<head>Traduction</head>
				<p>Le 4 Sminthios, aux Damateres (Déméters), (sacrifier) une brebis pleine. </p>
			</div>
			<div type="commentary">
				<head>Commentary</head>

				<p>The inscription is one of a large number of extracts from a sacrificial calendar inscribed or recodified in the
					late Classical or early Hellenistic period and disseminated at various local sanctuaries, presumably as
					punctual reminders and short regulations in and of themselves (for the early beginning of such excerpts, cf.
					here <ref target="CGRN_62">CGRN 62</ref> and <ref target="CGRN_63">CGRN 63</ref>, both from Lindos). The
					excerpts perhaps come from the general sacrificial calendar of the unified city of Rhodes or perhaps equally
					probably from that of Kamiros itself. See e.g. <ref target="CGRN_110">CGRN 110</ref> for further examples from
					Kamiros; e.g. <ref target="CGRN_115">CGRN 115</ref> for others from Lindos. For a general discussion of these
					excerpts, see Segre and Carbon forthc. Though the inscription appears later than most of these Hellenistic
					excerpts (notably because of its lettering), it nonetheless preserves a style and layout typical of the
					earlier excerpts from the sacrificial calendar; it may therefore have been reinscribed in the late Hellenistic
					or early Roman period.</p>

				<p>The excerpt is rather brief in this case (for other very brief excerpts, cp. <ref target="CGRN_112">CGRN
						112</ref>, Kamiros, and both <ref target="CGRN_115">CGRN 115</ref> and <ref target="CGRN_116">CGRN
						116</ref>, Lindos). Since the small stele was found in the territory of Kamiros rather than in that city
					(at this time, a deme of Rhodes), it may have originally belonged to a local sanctuary of the goddesses in the
					countryside. In this light, it is also noteworthy that the inscription does not mention any officials
					responsible for the sacrifice, which contrasts with all of the other excerpts found at Kamiros. A pair of
					excerpts at Lindos, <ref target="CGRN_115">CGRN 115</ref> and <ref target="CGRN_116">CGRN 116</ref>, do not
					mention any cult personnel either and also come from the countryside. Possibly the worshippers in these rural
					settings were expected to perform the sacrifice themselves.</p>

				<p>The cult was concerned with the worship of multiple "Demeters", most probably the goddess Demeter and her
					daughter Kore; the pair are more commonly called "twin goddesses" in the dual, as at Eleusis: cf. <ref target="CGRN_8">CGRN 8</ref>, line 5. A strong parallel at Kamiros is presented by another pair of
					excerpts from the sacrificial calendar at Lindos, which attested to a sacrifice for "Demeter" or the
					"Damateres", depending on the restoration on the Acropolis there, cf. <ref target="CGRN_179">CGRN 179</ref>,
					line 2. An inscription explicitly mentioning the Damateres near this spot is <bibl type="abbr" n="Lindos II">Lindos II</bibl> 183, ca. 200-170 BC, marking the cult-site of the goddess and of Zeus Damatrios for the
						<foreign>patra</foreign> of the Haliadai. Both these Lindian sacrifices seem to have taken place on early
					dates (the 7th and the 12th), probably also, as here at Kamiros, in the month Sminthios (the 8th month on
					Rhodes, ca. March/April, which marked the transition between the winter and early spring; cf. the
					reconstruction of the Rhodian calendar refined by Badoud and generally adopted here; for a different view, see
					Iversen). The goddess or goddesses honoured at Lindos were also the recipients of a pregnant animal—definitely
					a pregnant sow, and possibly a pregnant sheep, too. For the sacrifice of a pregnant ewe to Demeter, see here
						<ref target="CGRN_32">CGRN 32</ref> (Thorikos), lines 36-39 (for the Chloia, probably a ewe). For this
					offering, also relatively commonly found for others goddesses, see <ref target="CGRN_56">CGRN 56</ref>
					(Marathonian Tetrapolis), col. I, lines 20-37 (unknown goddess in Pyanopsion), and col. II, lines 11-16 (Daira
					in Gamelion); <ref target="CGRN_84">CGRN 84</ref> (Salaminioi), line 93 (Athens Skiras in Maimakterion); and
						<ref target="CGRN_85">CGRN 85</ref> (Kos), line 24 (Athena Polias). Overall, these offerings for the
					Damateres at Kamiros and the probably analogous goddess(es) at Lindos must have marked the beginning of the
					Spring and, as with other rituals for Demeter, will probably have had a connection with agricultural
					propitiation, in this case at a critical juncture in the year: the onset of the growth of new cereal plants.
					Cp. also, perhaps, the cult of the Materes at Eleutherna: see <ref target="CGRN_210">CGRN 210</ref>, lines
					B3-4.</p>
			</div>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>
